<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oliver Schwartz</title>
    <link>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Oliver Schwartz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 11:10:00 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://oliverschwartz.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Memoryless distributions in practice</title>
      <link>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/posts/teller/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 11:10:00 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/posts/teller/</guid>
      <description>I came across this probability problem in an MIT course and I thought the solution was a good illustration of the memoryless property of some distributions.
The problem: Suppose you are at a bank. You find that all three tellers are busy serving other customers, and there are no other customers in the queue. Assume that the service times for you and for each of the customers being served are i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A puzzle involving inverses</title>
      <link>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/posts/exp-puzzle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 10:16:00 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/posts/exp-puzzle/</guid>
      <description>Suppose we have the following two functions:
 $y = a^x$ $x = a^y$  You are told that there is one intersection point. Find this intersection point and the corresponding value of $a$.
Let&amp;rsquo;s begin by rearranging the second function to get it in terms of $y$: $$ y = \log_a x = \frac{\ln x}{\ln a} $$
Let&amp;rsquo;s define another function, $f(x)$, do be the difference between these two functions: $ f(x) = a^x - \frac{\ln x}{\ln a}.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 20:07:29 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/contact/</guid>
      <description>Feel free to email me at oliver(dot)p(dot)schwartz(at)gmail(dot)com</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 20:07:05 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description>Multidimensional cointegration: signal generation and analysis on Eurodollar futures. Paper. Going Viral: A virally themed game built with Three.js and Cannon.js. Play here Prediction engine for the NBA All-Star fan vote: Ball-game, or social media game? Repository and white paper. Facial generation with CelebA data set: pattern searching in data. Code. Logistic regression on an artificial data set: predicting the tastiness of papayas. Code. Optimal stopping problem: derivation and simulation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The maiden post: the singular value decomposition</title>
      <link>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/posts/svd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 19:56:57 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/posts/svd/</guid>
      <description>Singular value decomposition    Singular value decomposition (SVD) is perhaps the most interesting and fundamental theorem of linear algebra. Generally speaking, it says that any matrix can be factored into the product of three matrices with specific properties, one of which is a diagonal matrix. (In this post we will just assume our matrices are real-valued).
Specifically, the SVD of a real matrix $A \in \mathbb{R}^{m \times n}$ can be written as the product of three matrices $U$, $\Sigma$, $V^T.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 19:50:16 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://oliverschwartz.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a software engineer and problem solver from Sydney, Australia.
As an undergrad, I studied at Princeton University, majoring in computer science. I also rowed on the men&amp;rsquo;s heavyweight crew team. At Princeton, I won the Shapiro prize for academic excellence and the 1916 cup for the varsity athlete with highest academic standing. I was the president of Tau Beta Pi (the engineering honor society) and graduated Summa Cum Laude (3.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
